Guide to the John Gunther Papers 1935-1967
University of Chicago Library
- Series X: Eisenhower-The Man and the Symbol
  The correspondence is not extensive, filling only two folders. Among the Informational heading is a memorandum from a Look official on Eisenhower as president of Columbia University. The post-publication correspondence comes from readers who had minor corrections to suggest.
  The majority of the notes are interview notes. Gunther interviewed military officials on Eisenhower's SHAPE staff, journalists, and several European statesmen. Among them are Eisenhower himself, General Alfred M. Grunther, Jean Monnet, and General Lauris Norstad.
  - Subseries 1: Original Manuscripts-Look Articles
    - Part One-"Inside Ike" (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Part Two-"What Can We Expect of Eisenhower?" (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Part Three-"Why the Russians Won't Fight in Europe" (unpublished) (1st and 2nd drafts) (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Original Manuscripts-Eisenhower, the Man and the Symbol
    - Chapter 1 The Man (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 2 The Career (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 3 Eisenhower and the War (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 4 The Job (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 5 The Future (Box 63, Folder 8)
    - Appendix I Interlude in Sicily (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - Bibliography (Box 63, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3: Printer's Copy
    - Title page, Dedication, Note, Table of Contents (Box 63, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 1 The Man (Box 63, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 2 The Background (Box 63, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 3 The Career (Box 63, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 4 The Job (Box 63, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 5 The Future (Box 63, Folder 16)
    - Appendix I With Eisenhower in Sicily Appendix II Eisenhower's Guildhall speech Appendix III Honors, Citations, and Decorations (Box 63, Folder 17)
    - Bibliography (Box 63, Folder 18)
    - Inserts for Galley Proofs (Box 63, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 4: Research Materials-Interview Notes
    - Airey, General Sir Terence (chief of Intelligence, SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish (Editor, Foreign Affairs) (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - Auriol, Vincent (President of France) (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - Biddle, ? (U.S. General) (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Bruce, David K.E. (American Ambassador to France) (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - Cannon, Col. C. Craig (ADC to Gen. Eisenhower) (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - Carroll, Col. Paul T. (Military Assistant to General Eisenhower) (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - Cowles, Gardner (Journalist) (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (General of the Army, Commander SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Fodor, M. W. (Journalist) (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Grunther, General Alfred M. (SHAPE Chief of Staff) (Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Kerr, Walter (Journalist) (Box 64, Folder 12)
    - Lawrence, Col. J. B. L. ("Jock") (Deputy for Plans and Public Affairs, PID, SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 13)
    - Michaelis, Gen. John H. ("Mike") (Charge of Plans for European Army, SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 14)
    - Monnet, Jean (French statesman) (Box 64, Folder 15)
    - Montgomery, Field Marshal Sir Bernard L. (Deputy Supreme Commander, SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 16)
    - Norstad, Lauris (U.S. General, Commander USAFE, C.-in-c. Central Air Forces Europe, SHAPE) (Box 64, Folder 17)
    - Pleven, Rene (French Premier) (Box 64, Folder 18)
    - Tyler, ? (Journalist) (Box 64, Folder 19)
    - White, S. (Journalist?) (Box 64, Folder 20)
    - Wood, Robert J. (U.S. Colonel, Secretary) (Box 64, Folder 21)
    - "Cy" (Cyrus Sulzberger, journalist) (Box 64, Folder 22)
    - "Steve W." (Box 64, Folder 23)
    - "Toddy W." (Box 64, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous interview notes (Box 64, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 5: Miscellaneous Materials
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 64, Folder 26)
    - Watch sheets, check sheets, proof sheets (Box 64, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous typewritten notes (Box 64, Folder 28)
  - Subseries 6: Correspondence
    - Pre-publication (Box 64, Folder 29)
    - Post-publication (Box 64, Folder 30)
- Series XI: Inside Africa
  INSIDE AFRICA. published in 1955, is one of Gunther's longest books, running to over 950 pages. The materials concerning this book are contained in twenty-two boxes. The manuscripts for this work are as follows:
  2. Specialist Review copy. However, only those pages with comments are included as well as memoranda prepared by Gunther's "experts"
  3. First Revision or Second Draft, which is a heavily revised copy of a carbon copy of the corrected original manuscript
  4. Printer's copy, which is essentially the Third Draft because of the heavy revisions, more so than in any other of Gunther's works
  5. Galley proofs, with author's corrections.
  While in Africa, Gunther prepared numerous articles for publication in popular magazines. He used portions of these articles, though in a revised form, in his published book. The twenty-one articles are included in the collection, some in original manuscript, some carbon copies, some clippings.
  The informational correspondence is extensive and has been arranged by country or area and then alphabetically. Gunther corresponded with numerous American and British diplomatic officials, government officials, United Nations officials, businessmen and many others. Among the letters of interest are those of Edgar Sengier, the head of Union Miniere in the Congo; the U. S. Ambassador to Ethiopia, Joseph Simonson; a memorandum from the Governor of the gold Coast (Ghana), Sir Charles Arden Clarke who read Gunther's chapter on that country in advance of publication; C. L. Simpson, Liberian Ambassador to the United States; Hamilton Fish Armstrong, editor of Foreign Affairs, on Morocco and North Africa; David Stirling, president of the Capricorn Africa Society; South African attorney and novelist Harry Bloom; the Governor of Tanganyika, Sir Edward Twining; and H. V. L. Swanzy, a high official in the Gold Coast Government.
  The Post-publication correspondence is also extensive. It is primarily readers, response. Some of the letters, however, invite Gunther to address various groups, ask for additional information, or offer the correspondent's own views. The correspondence, which comes from all over the worlds, is generally favorable to Gunther's work, but many of the letters take exception to his interpretation, especially those from white settlers in Africa, and particularly in the Union of South Africa. Among the letters of interest are two from Dr. Hastings Banda, at present prime minister of Nyasaland, but then living in the Gold Coast; R. R. Knight, a member of the Canadian House of Commons, and Ann Morisett, an American novelist. Specific correspondence, commenting upon or criticizing individual chapters or parts of chapters, suggesting revisions, pointing out errors of fact, spelling or grammar, is arranged alphabetically by country or area and then alphabetically by author. General correspondence relating to the book as a whole or a substantial portion is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  The research notes are arranged by country or by area. The majority of the notes are interview notes and, where possible, the interviewee has been identified. Gunther states that he interviewed 1503 persons while preparing his African book. Included among them were governors, colonial officials, embassy and consular staffs, journalist, African chieftains, missionaries, businessmen, nationalists, United Nations personnel, and private citizens. A representative list of the many interviewed would include General Mohammed Naguib, then dictator of Egypt; Kwame Nkrumah, prime minister of the Gold Coast; Edgar Segnier of Union Miniere in the Belgian Congo; the king of Ruanda; U. N. official Ralph Bunche; Zulu Chief Albert Luthuli; author Alan Paton; J. G. Strijdo-, then prime minister of the Union of South Africa; Walter White of the N.A.A. C.P.; the Pasha of Marrakesh; General Augustin Gulliaume, President-General of Morocco; Roy Welenski, white extremist leader of Northern Rhodesia; Sylvanus Olympio, then nationalist leader in Togoland, and Father Trever Huddleston, Anglican missionary in South Africa.
  There are also numerous memoranda, articles, and circulars prepared by others for Gunther's use. Included among these notes are a private mimeographed memoranda by Chester Bowles on his 1955 trip to Africa, biographical notes on Various African personalities, and a copy of an article by Santha Rama Rau entitled "The Trial of Jomo Kenyatta," of which only a portion was published in The Reporter.
  - Subseries 1: Original Manuscript
    - Table of Contents, Preface (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Introduction (1) (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 1 The Sultan of Morocco (2) (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 2 Moroccan Backdrop (3) (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 3 Arab World in North Africa (4) (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 4 The French, the Nationalists, the Americans (5) (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 5 Lord of the Atlas (6) (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 6 Tangier and Return (7) (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 7 Algeria-From Firates to Petroleum (8) (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 8 Inside Nowhere-The Sahara (9) (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 8A The Tunisian Complex (10) (Box 65, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 9 Libya, or a Child Learning to Walk (11) (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 12 Crisis and Development in Egypt (12) (Box 65, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 12A Nasser to Naguib to Nasser (13) (Box 65, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 13 The Nile and the Sudan (14) (Box 65, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 13 Haile Selassie, Emperor of Ethiopia (15) (Box 65, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 14 More About Ethiopia, Eritrea, and the Somalis (16) (Box 65, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 16 Forward to Bantu Africa (17) (Box 65, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 17 Kenya-The Land and the People (18) (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 18 Kenya; British Rule in Africa (19) (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 18A Kenya-The Mau Maus (20) (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 19 East Africa-Animals (21) (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 20 The Wonderful World of Tanganyika (22) (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 21 Hope and Crisis in Uganda (23) (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 24 The Union of South Africa-Successors to Malan (24) (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 25 The Union-Country. Towns, and Issues (25) (Box 66, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 26 The Union The Blacks and the Browns (26) (Box 66, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 27 The Union- Gold, diamonds, and South West Africa (27) (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 29 Medicine Murder in Basutoland (28) (Box 66, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 30 Portuguese Africa (29) (Box 66, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 31 The Rhodesias and Central African Federation (30) (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 31A More About Rhodesia and Nyasaland (31) (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 32 Congo I-Belgian Policy in Africa (32) (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 33 Congo II-Uranium, Giants, Pygmies (33) (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 33 French Rule in Black Africa (34) (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 33 A Visit to Dr. Albert Schweitzer (35) (Box 67, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 34 Complexities and Achievements in Nigeria (36-37) (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 35 Nigeria-Its Inflammatory Politics (38) (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 36 The Nigerian North (39) (Box 67, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 37 Prime Minister Nkrumah of the Gold coast (40) (Box 67, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 38 House of Commons in Black Miniature (41) (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 39 The Gold Coast and the Golden Stool (42) (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 41 Mr. Tubman of Liberia (43-44) (Box 67, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 42 Dakar and French West Africa (45) (Box 67, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 45... And To Conclude (46) (Box 67, Folder 14)
    - Sources (Box 67, Folder 15)
    - Acknowledgements, Bibliography (Box 67, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 2: Comments on Manuscript
    - Comments on margin of mss, by Cass Canfield, Eric Larrabee and Eugene Exman (Only pages with corrections and comments) (Box 68, Folder 1)
    - Comments by Cass Canfield, et al. (continued) (Box 68, Folder 2)
    - Comments on Chapters 2-8 (North Africa) by Roger Vaurs of French Press Service (Box 68, Folder 3)
    - Comments on Chapter 9 (Libya) by H. Villard, American Minister to Libya (Box 68, Folder 4)
    - Comments on Chapters 13-14 (Ethiopia) by A. H. Garretson, American Folder 6: Comments on Chapter 41 (Liberia) by Adolph Dubs (Box 68, Folder 5)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Introduction, Chapter 16 (Forward to Bantu Africa) (Box 68, Folder 7)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapters 12-12A (Egypt) (Box 68, Folder 8)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 13 (The Nile and The Sudan) (Box 68, Folder 9)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapters 17, 18, 18A (Kenya) (Box 68, Folder 10)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 19 (Animals) (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 20 (Tanganyika), Zanzibar (Box 68, Folder 12)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 21 (Uganda) (Box 68, Folder 13)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapters 31-31A (The Rhodesias) (Box 68, Folder 14)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 29 (High Commission Territories, South Africa) (Box 68, Folder 15)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 34 (Nigeria) (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 35 (Nigeria) (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 36 (Nigeria) (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapters 37-39 (Nigeria) (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - Comments by Richard Webb et al. of British Information Services- Chapter 45 (Conclusion) (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: First Revision (Second Draft)
    - Table of Contents, Preface (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 1 Dark Continent Becoming Light (Introduction in Orig. ms.) (Box 69, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 1 The Sultan of Morocco (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 2 Moroccan Backdrop (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 3 Arab World in North Africa (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 4 The French, the Nationalist, The Americans (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 5 Lord of the Atlas (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 6 Tangier and Tetuan (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 7 Algeria-From Pirates to Petroleum (Box 69, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 8 Inside Nowhere-The Sahara (Box 69, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 8A The Tunisian Complex (Box 69, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 9 Libya, or a Child Learning to Walk (Box 69, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 13 Haile Selassie, Emperor of Ethiopia (Box 69, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 29 Medicine Murder in Basutoland (Box 69, Folder 19)
    - Chapter 30 Portuguese Africa (Box 69, Folder 20)
    - Chapter 32 Congo I-Belgian Policy in Africa (Box 69, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 33 Congo II-Uranium in the Haut Katanga (Box 69, Folder 22)
    - Chapter 33 Congo II-Uranium, Pygmies, Giants (Box 69, Folder 23)
    - Chapter 33 A Visit to Dr. Albert Schweizer (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 33 A Visit to Dr. Albert Schweitzer (3rd Draft) (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 34 Complexities and Achievements in Nigeria (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 35 Nigeria-Its Inflammatory Politics (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 36 The Nigerian North (Corrected pages only) (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 37 Prime Minister Nkrumah of the Gold Coast (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 38 House of Commons in Black Miniature (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 39 The Gold Cost and the Golden Stool (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 41 Mr. Tubman of Liberia (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 46 And to Conclude (Box 70, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 4: Printer's Copy
    - Chapter 1 Dark Continent Becoming Right (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 2 The Sultan of Morocco (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 3 Moroccan Backdrop (Box 70, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 4 Arab World in North Africa (Box 70, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 5 The French, the Nationalists, the Americans (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 6 Lord of the Atlas (Box 70, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 7 Tangier and Tetuan (Box 70, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 8 Brief Word About Algeria (Box 70, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 9 Inside Nowhere-The Sahara (Box 70, Folder 19)
    - Chapter 10 The Tunisian Complex (Box 70, Folder 20)
    - Chapter 11 Libya, or a Child Learning to Walk (Box 70, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 12 Crisis and Development in Egypt (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 13 Nasser to Naguib to Nasser (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 14 The Nile and the Sudan (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 15 Haile Selassie, Emperor of Ethiopia (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 16 More About Ethiopia, Eritrea, and the Somalis (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 17 Forward to Bantu Africa (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 18 Kenya, The Land and people (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 19 Kenya, British Rule in Africa (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 20 Kenya, The Mau Maus (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 21 East Africa-Animals (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 22 The Wonderful World of Tanganyika (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 23 Hope and Crisis in Uganda (Box 71, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 24 The Union of South Africa-Successors to Malan (Box 71, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 25 The Union-Country, Towns, and Issues (Box 71, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 26 The Union-The Blacks and the Browns (Box 71, Folder 15)
    - Chapter The Union-Gold, Diamonds, and South West Africa (Box 71, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 28 Medicine Murder in Basutoland (Marked Ch. 29 on ms.) (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 29 Portuguese Africa (Marked Ch. 30 on ms.) (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 30 The Rhodesias and Central African Federation (Marked Ch. 31 on ms.) (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 31 More about Rhodesia and Nyasaland (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 32 Congo I. Belgian Policy in Africa (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 33 Congo II-Uranium, Pygmies, Giants (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 34 French Rule in Black Africa (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 35 A Visit to Dr. Albert Schweitzer (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 36 Introduction to British West Africa (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 37 Complexities and Achievements in Nigeria (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 38 Nigeria-its Inflammatory Politics (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 39 The Nigerian North (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 40 Prime Minister Nkrumah of the Gold coast (Box 72, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 41 House of Commons in Black Miniature (Box 72, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 42 The Gold Coast and the Golden Stool (Box 72, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 43 Mr. Tubman of Liberia (Box 72, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 44 Monrovian Doctrine (Box 72, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 45 Dakar and French West Africa (Box 72, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 46... And to Conclude (Box 72, Folder 19)
    - Acknowledgements, Bibliography (Box 72, Folder 20)
    - Notes, Names, Sources, Map. (Box 72, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 5: Galley Proofs
    - Chapters 1-3 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 4-6 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 7-9 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 10-12 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 13-15 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Chapters 16-18 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Chapters 19-21 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Chapters 22-23 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - Chapters 28-30 (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - Chapters 31-33 (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - Chapters 34-36 (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - Chapters 37-39 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - Chapters 40-42 (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - Chapters 43-46 (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - Acknowledgments, Bibliography, and Sources (Box 73, Folder 15)
    - Proofs for promotional excepts (Box 73, Folder 16)
    - Photographs-North Africa (Box 73, Folder 17)
    - Photographs-John Gunther and Kwame Nkrumah (Box 73, Folder 18)
    - Photographs of military ceremony in Ethiopia, with Haile Selassie (Box 73, Folder 19)
    - Photographs of Point IV medical team in Libya (Box 73, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, pictures, postcards (Box 73, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 6: Manuscripts, Carbon Copies, Published Copies of Articles
    - "Africa's Black Magicians" (Carbon copy, published as "A Report on Africa's Black Magic," The American Weekly, N.Y. Journal-American clipping) (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - "Africa's Magic Mountain" (Original ms.) (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - "Arabian Nights and Days-Morocco" (Reader's Digest clipping) (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - "Britain's Best Bet in Africa" (Carbon copy) (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - "Can We Stop Communism in Africa" (Carbon copy) (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - "Chivalry" (Original ms.) (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - "The Dictator Who Laughs" (Carbon copy, N. Y. Herald-Tribune clipping) (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - "The General, the Sultan, and the Pasha" (Carbon copy, This Week, N. Y. Herald-Tribune clipping) (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - "The Gold Coast" (Hektograph copy, for Colliers) (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - "Inside Egypt" (Reader's Digest clipping) (Box 74, Folder 10)
    - "Inside Nowhere (A Trip to the Sahara)" (Carbon copy corrected) (Box 74, Folder 11)
    - "Iola" (Original ms., 2nd draft, published as "The Lion was a Lady", This Week, N. Y. Herald-Tribune) (Box 74, Folder 12)
    - "Is the White Man Finished in Africa" (Original ms., Reader's Digest clipping) (Box 74, Folder 13)
    - "A Jackpot of Diamonds" (Carbon copy, partial copy) (Box 74, Folder 14)
    - "The Man Who Saved Kenya" (original ms.) (Box 74, Folder 15)
    - "Murder, Magic, and the Mau-Maus" (Carbon copy, 2nd draft, The American Weekly, N. Y. Journal-American clipping) (Box 74, Folder 16)
    - "Murder Most Foul in Basutoland" (Original ms., 2nd draft, 3rd draft) (Box 74, Folder 17)
    - "The Story of Edgar Sengier" (Original ms., 2nd draft) (Box 74, Folder 18)
    - "Taking the Veil Off Moslem Women" (Carbon copy, published as "Romance Comes to Morocco," The American Weekly, N. Y. Journal-American) (Box 74, Folder 19)
    - "Training Africans to be Frenchmen" (Galley proof) (Box 74, Folder 20)
    - "The World's Most Fantastic Airline" (Carbon copy) (Box 74, Folder 21)
    - "Inside Africa" Lecture (Original ms.) (Box 74, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 7: Correspondence-International and Pre-publication
    - Belgian Congo (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - British Africa (general) (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Egypt (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Ethiopia (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - French Africa (general) (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Gold Coast (Ghana) (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - Kenya (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Liberia (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Libya (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - Madagascar (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - Morocco (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - Portuguese Africa (Box 75, Folder 12)
    - The Rhodesias (Box 75, Folder 13)
    - Dr. Albert Schweitzer (Box 75, Folder 14)
    - Somaliland (Box 75, Folder 15)
    - The Sudan (Box 75, Folder 16)
    - Tanganyika (Box 75, Folder 17)
    - Uganda (Box 75, Folder 18)
    - Union of South Africa (Box 75, Folder 19)
    - Zanzibar (Box 75, Folder 20)
    - General (Box 75, Folder 21)
    - Letters of Introduction (Box 75, Folder 22)
    - Readers' Digest; Collier's Magazine (Box 75, Folder 23)
    - Personal (Box 75, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 8: Correspondence-Post-publication
    - Animals (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - Basutoland (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - Belgian Congo (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Egypt (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Ethiopia (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Gold Coast (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Kenya (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Liberia (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Libya (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Morocco (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Nigeria (Box 76, Folder 11)